Finding Aid for Dept. of History (University of Michigan) records, 1884-2011
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Dept. of History (University of Michigan) records
1884-2011
1970-1990
University of Michigan. Dept. of History.
87137 Bimu C26 2
The Department of History is an academic department within the University of Michigan established in 1845. The department was originally part of the School of Political Science but separated in 1910 and became a separate department within the College of Literature, Science, and Arts. The collection ranges from 1884 to 2011 with the bulk of the material from the 1970s and the 1980s. The records contain information on administrative matters and operations within the department, including correspondence, memos, meeting minutes, committee information, faculty information, and student affairs.
13.4 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
These records were received from the department beginning in 1941 (donor no. 1442 ). The largest transfers were in 1984 and 2012
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The Department of History records are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy. Restricted material includes personnel-related files, including search, review, promotion, and tenure files; student educational records; client/patient records; and records of executive officers of the university.
The Department of History record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Personnel Related Records -- Boxes 14
The University of Michigan Department of History, founded in 1845, began by teaching ancient history to freshman, medieval history to sophomores, and modern history to juniors. Andrew Dickson White, coming from Yale in 1857, was a pioneer in historical teaching methods and took the position of Professor of History and English Literature, becoming the first professor of Modern History. White was heavily involved in the university and encouraged students to start a three-year track of studying history. In 1862, Charles Kendall Adams became the second staff member to teach history, and he took over after White left. Adams is best known for introducing the seminary method of teaching at the university. In 1871, President James Angell added courses on international law and treatises to the history department. The Department of History officially became part of the School of Political Science in 1881. George Knight became the first student to graduate with a doctorate in history from the University of Michigan in 1884. In 1885, Richard Hudson became department chair of history and proceeded to become Dean of the Department of Literature, Science and Arts. In 1890 the second doctorate in history was awarded to Ephraim Adams and the School of Political Science was absorbed into the Literary Department, along with the Department of History.
In 1894, Earle Wilbur Dow taught the first history classes to be offered during the University of Michigan's newly established summer term. A course focused specifically on American History was established in 1896. In the early twentieth century, courses on ancient history were a minority, but courses on English history began to grow in popularity. In 1908 the general course on English history was able to be supplemented for the introductory course on European history, which was a prerequisite for all other work in the department. In addition, attendance in courses on medieval and American history increased and the Department of History had to expand its number of faculty. In 1910 the Department of History broke apart from the School of Political Science and became an independent department under the College of Literature, Science, and the Arts (LSA) with Jesse Reeves as Chairman.
In 1914 the department hired Arthur Edward Romilly Boak, the first faculty member to be a specialist on ancient history. Boak allowed the course on ancient history to be accessible to freshman and it was able to serve as a substitute for the English history and European history introductory classes. His success at teaching quickly escalated his position and he became Chairman of the Department of History in 1930. In 1916 William Lytle Schurz offered the first history class on Latin-American history, and Boak proceeded to teach a class on military history. To further the diversity of classes offered by the department, Arthur Lyon Cross began teaching seminars on the Tudor and Stuart periods of England and in 1919 he was able to teach a specialized class on the British Empire. When Schurz left, the Latin-American position was left empty for a year until Arthur Scott Aiton began teaching it again in 1921. Aiton also influenced the growth of courses on Hispanic-American history. In 1924, the field of modern European history was strengthened by Albert Hyma, and the following year Nicholas S. Kaltchas joined the staff and began teaching courses on the Near East. In 1930 a class on the History of Western Civilization was offered and replaced the three introductory courses. John William Stanton became part of the faculty in 1932 and added to the Near East classes while also developing courses for the Far East. Lewis George Vander Velde came to the university in 1929 as a staff member of the history department and in 1935 he began accumulating documents on the history of the university and the state. In 1938 he was appointed Director of the Michigan Historical Collections, now the Bentley Historical Library.
In 1950 the Department of History, originally housed in Haven Hall, was forced to move to the building that housed the Michigan Historical Collections due to a fire in Haven Hall. In 1952, the department was able to move back to Haven Hall. Howard Ehrmann became Chairman in 1953, and John Bowditch in 1960. As of 1964, the Department of History held the place of second most popular field of concentration within the College of LSA, with English holding the first place position. Through the years, the Department has fought for the position and dropped to third place on occasion, being replaced by such concentrations as Mathematics and Psychology. In 1964, the Asian Studies branch of the department was broadened and students were allowed to focus on Asiatic history for their degree. After the University of Michigan switched to the trimester system in 1966, the department expanded the graduate program in comparative studies by introducing new comparative courses. A program in the History of Science was also introduced at this time. In 1969, Sidney Fine was appointed Chairman of the department. In 1971 Bradford Perkins took the position of Chairman and Gerhard Weinberg in 1972. Also in 1972, the department was given a grant to start offering courses on Comparative Studies in Historical Cultures, open to freshman and sophomores. David Bean assumed chairmanship of the department in 1974. In 1975, Roger Hackett took over as Chairman, followed by Marvin Becker and Jacob Price. In 1983, the Department of History was nationally ranked number five in the quality of faculty among all history departments across the United States. Albert Feuerwerker was appointed Chairman in 1984 and Thomas Trautmann took over in 1987.
The 1987-1988 term witnessed a large overhaul of the graduate studies program with changes aimed at incorporating comparative and interdisciplinary aspects into the program. To accompany this overhaul, the Graduate Organization of Students in History was also started. In 1989, as the number of undergraduate students increased, the department opted to offer an increasing amount of diversified courses for undergraduate students. William Rosenberg took over as Chairman in 1990. The same year, a joint doctoral program was offered in history and anthropology. In 1993 a program focused on British Studies was started. In 1994 Maris Vinovskis was appointed Chairman and the Department offered the first class in Spanish Language combined with the Latin American survey courses. In 1995, the department began offering seminary courses that were open to incoming students to allow them to experience classes other than large survey courses. Rebecca Scott followed Maris Vinovskis and became Chairman in 1996 and the Department offered a language class on Modern German. In 1997 the Department introduced courses that focused on English composition through the writing of history. A course focused on teaching pedagogy to graduate students was added in 1998. A minor in history was offered by the Department for the first time in 1999. In 2000 Frederick Cooper became Chairman and Sonya Rose took over in 2002. In 2005 the Institute for Historical Studies was established. Mary Kelley became Chairman in 2006 and Geoff Eley took the position in 2008.
The University of Michigan Department of History records contain a large range of documentation regarding the operation, administration, statistics, faculty, and proceedings of the department. The bulk of the collection originally arrived at the Bentley in 1988 and a large addition was made in 2012. The collection spans from 1884 to 2011, however, the bulk of the content dates between 1970 and 1990. The collection is divided into fifteen series: Awards, College of LSA, Committees, Correspondence, Department, Faculty, Finances, General, Graduate Program, International Relations, Lecture Series, Partner Institutions, Programs, Publications, Student Affairs, and University of Michigan.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Dept. of History.; History--Study and teaching.
- Awards
  The Awards series (1951-1998) contains information on various awards presented in relation to the Department of History, including what the awards are and who they were presented to. The bulk of this is in regards to the Distinguished Teaching Fellow Award.
  - Allan Nevins Prize, 1970-1983 (Box 1)
  - Alumnae Athena Award, 1975; 1977 (Box 1)
  - Class of Award, 1923; 1951-1955; 1975-1996; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Distinguished Teaching Fellow Award, 1968-1995; 8 folders (Box 1)
  - Graduate Student Instructor Award, 1994; 1998 (Box 1)
  - Warner Rice Humanities Award, 1986-1987 (Box 1)
- College of L.S.A.
  The College of LSA series (1932-1991), short for the College of Literature, Science, and the Arts, contains files related to the Dean's Office and the various committees associated with the College. The information is not necessarily specific to the Department of History, but covers broader information that would have been relevant to the department since it is contained within the college.
  - Chairman Meeting, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Checkpoint Brochure, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Committees
    - Curricular Flexibility of Superior Students, 1956 (Box 1)
    - Curriculum Committee, 1950-1959; 1973-1987; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Dean Search Committee, 1958 (Box 1)
    - Executive Committee, 1988-1991; 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Great Books Committee, undated (Box 1)
    - Nominating Committee, 1988 (Box 1)
    - Priorities Committee, 1976-1977 (Box 1)
    - Religious History Committee, 1956 (Box 1)
  - Dean's Office
    - General, 1932-1937; 1940; 1952-1956; 1969-1974; 12 folders (Box 1)
    - General, 1975-1983; 5 folders (Box 2)
    - Associate Dean Allen, Sally, 1988-1989 (Box 2)
    - Associate Dean Cross, John, 1987-1995; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Associate Dean Ford, Richard, 1988 (Box 2)
    - Associate Dean Galler, Bernard, 1975-1979 (Box 2)
    - Associate Dean Mueller, Eva, 1974-1978 (Box 2)
    - Associate Dean Nissen, Eugene, 1975-1987 (Box 2)
    - Associate Dean Pollack, Henry, 1983 (Box 2)
    - Associate Dean Rabkin, Eric S., 1980-1983 (Box 2)
    - Associate Dean Rasmussen, Paul, 1978-1982 (Box 2)
    - Associate Dean Walker, Jack, 1984-1987; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Associate Dean Williams, William L., 1985-1986 (Box 2)
    - Associate Dean Zimmerman, William, 1981-1984; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Associate Dean Zorn, Jens, 1980-1982 (Box 2)
    - Credit Hour Trends in the Social Sciences, 1989-1996 (Box 2)
    - Cross Report, 1986 (Box 2)
    - Dean Frye, B.E., 1979-1980 (Box 2)
    - Dean Steiner, Peter, 1981-1989; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Focus Groups, 1998 (Box 2)
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 1970-1979 (Box 2)
  - Social Sciences Department Chairman, 1975 (Box 2)
  - The Undergraduate and the Lifetime Reading Habit, 1958; 3 folders (Box 3)
- Committees
  The Committees series (1931-2008) contains files of the Curriculum Committee, Executive Committee, and Search Committees as well as other departmental committees. A large group of the files come from the Curriculum Committee. Each committee folder contains memos, minutes and correspondence about the various activities and events that the committees were involved in. The committees are arranged alphabetically and then chronologically. Faculty meeting minutes are contained in the Department series.
  - Assignment of Members, 1969-1978 (Box 3)
  - College Priorities Committee, 1976 (Box 3)
  - Committee on Institutional Cooperation (C.I.C.), 1976-1980 (Box 3)
  - Curriculum Committee
    - General
      - No date, 1 folders (Box 3)
      - 1931-1948, 4 folders (Box 3)
      - 1956-1959, 1 folders (Box 3)
      - 1969-1985, 22 folders (Box 3)
      - 1998-2008, 9 folders (Box 3)
    - Afro-American History, 1968-1975 (Box 4)
    - Archival Program, 1971-1975 (Box 4)
    - Comparative History, 1971-1976 (Box 4)
    - Comparative Studies, 1983-1985 (Box 4)
    - Computers, 1983-1984 (Box 4)
    - Course Evaluating, 1978-1981 (Box 4)
    - Course Numbers, 1973; 1977-1978 (Box 4)
    - Doctoral Language Requirement, 1969-1972 (Box 4)
    - Doctorate in History and Philosophy, 1968 (Box 4)
    - English History, 1984 (Box 4)
    - External Degree Programs, 1975-1976 (Box 4)
    - Four Hour Proposal, 1966-1969 (Box 4)
    - Freshman Seminars, 1977 (Box 4)
    - Freshman/Sophomore, 1968-1973 (Box 4)
    - Freshman/Sophomore Study Courses, 1971-1972 (Box 4)
    - Graduate Program Proposal, 1967-1971 (Box 4)
    - History 600, 1968 (Box 4)
    - Language Requirements, 1971-1972 (Box 4)
    - Master's Degree Program, 1971-1972 (Box 4)
    - Modern Western Europe, undated (Box 4)
    - Profile of African Field, undated (Box 4)
    - Reforms in Curriculum, 1975-1978 (Box 4)
    - Undergraduate Degree Requirements, 1973 (Box 4)
  - Evaluation of Teaching Committee, 1972-1973 (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee
    - General, 1934-1969; 5 folders (Box 4)
    - General, 1968-1993; 14 folders (Box 5)
    - Reports to Department, 1968-1976 (Box 5)
  - Fellowship Committee, 1971-1974; 1977; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Graduate Program Study Committee, 1983 (Box 5)
  - Program Evaluation Committee, 1972-1974; 1976; 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Search Committee
    - African, 1960 (Box 6)
    - African History, 1982 (Box 6)
    - Afro-American, 1969 (Box 6)
    - American, 1966; 1972 (Box 6)
    - Ancient, 1962-1969 (Box 6)
    - Armenian Studies, 1979 (Box 6)
    - Asia, 1960 (Box 6)
    - Black History, 1975-1979 (Box 6)
    - Civil War, 1963 (Box 6)
    - Clements Library Director, 1976 (Box 6)
    - English History, 1948 (Box 6)
    - European History, 1966 (Box 6)
    - Far and Near East, 1947 (Box 6)
    - History of Medicine, 1975 (Box 6)
    - History of Science, 1969-1970 (Box 6)
    - Medieval, 1967 (Box 6)
    - Medieval-Renaissance, 1982 (Box 6)
    - Ottoman Empire, 1972-1976 (Box 6)
    - Southeast Asia, 1982-1983 (Box 14)
    - Student Participation Procedures, 1971 (Box 6)
    - Tudor and Stuart Eng, 1972-1973 (Box 6)
    - Twentieth Century, 1969-1971 (Box 6)
    - Women's History, 1983 (Box 14)
  - Student Steering Committee, 1968-1975 (Box 6)
  - Undergraduate Committee, 1977-1979 (Box 6)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series (1927-1996) contains general correspondence within the department as well as specific correspondence with significant individuals. The general correspondence is organized chronologically, and the individual correspondence have been separated out and are ordered alphabetically. Of particular note is the correspondence of Sydney (Syd) Mayer, who was a benefactor of the Department of History and created a fellowship in honor of Preston Slosson.
  - General, 1927-1933; 1939-1940; 1992-1996; 7 folders (Box 6)
  - Campanella, Anthony P., 1980-1981 (Box 6)
  - Departmental Communications, 1970-1981; 3 folders (Box 6)
  - External Correspondence, 1990-1991 (Box 6)
  - Internal Correspondence, 1990-1991; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Ledbetter, Robert, 1978-1986 (Box 6)
  - Leverette, B, 1981-1982 (Box 6)
  - Mayer, Sydney, 1980-1996; 7 folders (Box 7)
  - Witke, Charles, 1972-1973 (Box 7)
- Department
  The Department series (1928-2011) is a collection of both memos and meeting minutes from the Department of History. The meeting minutes date back to 1928 and end in 2011, though there are some sections missing. Particularly, there are no records between 1930 and 1954. The memos are complete from 1984 to 2001. Both memos and meeting minutes are organized chronologically.
  - Meeting Attendance Student Policy, 1974 (Box 7)
  - Meeting Minutes, 1928-1930; 1954-1978; 1984; 1990; 2011; 21 folders (Box 7)
  - Memos, 1984-2001; 31 folders (Box 8)
- Faculty
  The Faculty series (1939-1996) contains information regarding the staff in general, such as rules and regulations, and also information pertaining to specific staff members. Folders also contain information about the faculty or procedures of specific teaching divisions within the department.
  - Accountability, 1970-1972; 1982; 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Affirmative Action, 1970-1980; 1984; 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Afro-American History, 1996 (Box 8)
  - Aiton, Arthur S., 1956 (Box 8)
  - American Historians, 1977-1983 (Box 8)
  - American History Candidates, 1994-1996 (Box 14)
    [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2026 ]
  - Bentley Professorship, 1985 (Box 8)
  - Boak, A.E.R., 1946-1958 (Box 8)
  - Committee Work, 1949 (Box 9)
  - Course in American History Sources, 1975 (Box 9)
  - Cross, Arthur Lyon, 1940 (Box 9)
  - Department Retreat, 1986 (Box 9)
  - Dow, Earl W., 1944 (Box 9)
  - Dutch History, 1983-1984 (Box 9)
  - Early Modern History Candidates, 1996 (Box 14)
  - Economic History Position, 1986 (Box 14)
    [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2016 ]
  - Economic Status of the Faculty, 1976-1978 (Box 9)
  - English Composition Board, 1976-1982; 3 folders (Box 9)
  - Estabrook, George, 1996 (Box 14)
  - European History, 1982-1983 (Box 9)
  - Faculty Code, 1968-1976 (Box 9)
  - Far Eastern Languages and Literature, 1979 (Box 9)
  - Garber, Miriam, 1995 (Box 14)
    [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2025 ]
  - Germanic Languages and Literatures, 1982 (Box 9)
  - Grafton, Anthony, 1995 (Box 14)
  - Grievance Procedure, 1976 (Box 9)
  - Handicapped Regulations, 1977-1985 (Box 9)
  - Honors Council, 1972-1987 (Box 9)
  - Humphrey, Sally, 1994 (Box 14)
    [PR RESTRICTED until July 1 2024 ]
  - Hyma, Albert, 1946-1954 (Box 9)
  - Innovative Teaching, 1973 (Box 9)
  - Jewish History, 1984-1988 (Box 9)
  - Lamoreaux, Naomi, 1995 (Box 14)
  - Latin American Position, 1977-1982 (Box 9)
  - List of Faculty, 1980-1981 (Box 9)
  - Long, Dwight Clark, 1960 (Box 9)
  - Lurie, Edward, 1955-1956 (Box 9)
  - Marzolf, Kingsbury, 1981 (Box 9)
  - Malone, Dumas, 1940 (Box 9)
  - Medieval-Renaissance Collegium, 1972-1974 (Box 9)
  - Mellon, Stanley, 1954-1960 (Box 9)
  - Minority Recruitment, 1971-1975 (Box 9)
  - Modern Japanese History, 1995 (Box 14)
  - Ombudperson/University of Michigan, 1977 (Box 9)
  - Ottoman Position, 1976 (Box 9)
  - Placement, 1979-1980 (Box 9)
  - Position Approval Requests, 1970-1973 (Box 9)
  - Position Requests, 1980-1989; 3 folders (Box 9)
  - Powell, Alison M., 1979 (Box 9)
  - Procedures for Termination, 1978 (Box 9)
  - Promotions, 1976-1980; 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Promotions/Tenure/Renewal of Contracts, 1965-1978 (Box 9)
  - Quaife, Milo, 1939-1940 (Box 9)
  - Research, 1935-1940 (Box 9)
  - Rules and Regulations, Departmental, 1971-1972; 1974-1977 (Box 9)
  - Sample Letters, 1970-1976 (Box 9)
  - Schttler, Peter, 1996 (Box 14)
  - Scott, Julius, 1996 (Box 14)
  - Scott, S. Morley, 1956 (Box 9)
  - Sen, S. P., 1958-1959 (Box 9)
  - Shaheen, Anthony J., 1979 (Box 9)
  - Smoking in Classrooms, 1973-1976 (Box 9)
  - Smith-Rosenberg, Carroll, 1994-1995 (Box 14)
  - Stevenson, Brenda, 1995 (Box 14)
  - Women's Studies Director, 1995 (Box 14)
  - Stanton, John W., 1942-1943 (Box 10)
  - Summer School Teaching, 1979-1980 (Box 10)
  - Teaching Schedule, 1974-1975 (Box 10)
  - Teaching Values in History, 1975 (Box 10)
  - Tenure Decisions, 1981 (Box 10)
  - Unemployment Compensation, 1971-1975 (Box 10)
  - Vander Velde, Lewis G., 1953-1955 (Box 10)
  - Wheeler, Benjamin W., 1947 (Box 10)
  - White, Andrew Dickson Professorship, 1966-1976 (Box 10)
  - Women Faculty, 1968; 1970-1979; 1982 (Box 10)
  - Women's Club, 1972-1987 (Box 10)
  - Women's History, 1979; 1983 (Box 10)
  - Women's History Applicants, 1978 (Box 10)
- Finances
  The Finances series (1939-1995) includes information on budget, scholarships, grants, and other sources of funding available to both faculty and students who were part of the Department of History.
  - Boak Fellowship, 1968-1983 (Box 10)
  - Budget, 1939-1977; 5 folders (Box 10)
  - Budget Cut Comments, 1995 (Box 10)
  - Campaign for Michigan, 1984 (Box 10)
  - Colonial Dames, 1981 (Box 10)
  - Contributions, College Faculty Funds, 1983 (Box 10)
  - Cost Sharing, 1980 (Box 10)
  - Earhart Foundation, 1985-1989 (Box 10)
  - Faculty Fellowship Support, 1981 (Box 10)
  - Faculty Research Grants and Fellowships, 1976-1979 (Box 10)
  - Faculty Research Grants and Summer Fellowships, 1974-1976 (Box 10)
  - Fellowship Follow-up Study, 1969 (Box 10)
  - Fellowships for Graduates and Department, 1976-1979 (Box 10)
  - Graderships, 1982 (Box 10)
  - Josephine Nevins Keal and Bunting Fellowship, 1978-1981 (Box 10)
  - Knight, Gerald C. Donation, 1984 (Box 10)
  - Leave Balances, 1987 (Box 10)
  - Moore, Edward, 1975-1980 (Box 10)
  - Orla B. Taylor Scholarship Fund, 1949 (Box 10)
  - Phoenix Project, 1977-1980 (Box 10)
  - Power Exchange Scholarship, 1974-1975 (Box 10)
  - Priority Fund, 1978 (Box 10)
  - Study Abroad and Senior Scholarships, 1976-1982 (Box 10)
  - Work Study, 1982 (Box 10)
- General
  The General series (1952-2003) contains overarching information about the department. Of significance is information on the chairmanship of the department. The series also contains information on long-term planning for the department. Department memos and meeting minutes are located in the Department series.
  - Associate Chairmanship, 1971 (Box 10)
  - Brochure Regarding Field, 1982 (Box 10)
  - Chairman's File, 1952-1954 (Box 10)
  - Chairmanship, 1957-1959; 1970-1976; 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Clegg, Claude, 1997 (Box 10)
  - Department Organization, 1973 (Box 10)
  - Department Review, 1986-1990; 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Department Structure, 1972-1974 (Box 10)
  - Evaluation and Planning Project -- Phase 1, 1975-1976 (Box 10)
  - Evaluation and Planning Project -- Phase 2, 1977 (Box 10)
  - Files in Storage, 1976-1980 (Box 10)
  - Handbook Proposal, 1980-1983; 2 folders (Box 11)
  - History Department Facts, undated (Box 11)
  - List of Maps, undated (Box 11)
  - Long Term Plan, 2003 (Box 11)
  - Program Description, circa 1973 (Box 11)
- Graduate Program
  The Graduate Program series (1884-1988) contains information regarding the general Rackham graduate school of the University of Michigan as well as specific information in regards to students earning either a Masters or a Ph.D. from the Department of History.
  - Administration, 1975-1976 (Box 11)
  - Admissions, 1974-1980 (Box 11)
  - Advising, 1971-1972 (Box 11)
  - Alternate Careers, 1976 (Box 11)
  - A.M. in Comparative Studies in History, 1974 (Box 11)
  - Appeal Procedures, 1976 (Box 11)
  - Commission on Graduate Requirements, 1975-1976 (Box 11)